{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>A war over the electorate that ruled this region was ended by the Treaty of Teschen.</em> The ceding of lands held by Charles Theodore, a ruler of this region, led to this region's namesake war of succession. Three kings named Maximilian from the House of Wittelsbach ruled this region. One war named for this region is sometimes called the Potato War. In the nineteenth century, kings of this region included a king often described as \"mad\" named Ludwig II. For 10 points, name the largest state in Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Bavaria</u></b> [or Electorate of <b><u>Bavaria</u></b>; or Kingdom of <b><u>Bavaria</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>These people aimed to test the cases Morgan v. Virginia and Boynton v. Virginia.</em> Bull Connor claimed that no policeman stopped an attack on these people because it was Mother's Day. These people were led by Diane Nash and CORE founder James Farmer. JFK ensured police protection for these people after a Greyhound was bombed in Birmingham. For 10 points, name these activists who travelled on segregated buses in the summer of 1961.", "answer": "<b><u>Freedom Rider</u></b>s  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>Rudolph Virchow angered this specimen's discoverer by claiming he found gibbon remains.</em> This specimen consisted of few parts aside from a skull cap and a femur bone that was later determined to be from a modern human. This specimen was discovered by Eugene Dubois. It was initially named <em>Pithecanthropus erectus</em> before its later reclassification as <em>Homo erectus</em> <em>erectus</em>. For 10 points, name this supposed missing link between humans and apes found on an Indonesian island.", "answer": "<b><u>Java Man</u></b> [or <b><u>Pithecanthropus erectus</u></b> before mention; prompt on <b><u>Homo erectus</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>This group operates under the motto \"Unity, liberty, socialism.\"</em> This group led two coups in 1963 a month apart from each other, one of which occurred during Ramadan. This party's regime authorized the use of chemical weapons during the Halabja Massacre. This party, founded by Michel Aflaq, split into two opposing factions based in Iraq and Syria. For 10 points, name this pan-Arab political party whose members include the al-Assad family and Saddam Hussein.", "answer": "<b><u>Ba'ath</u></b> Party [or <b><u>Ba'athists</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This emperor is highly praised in the histories of Ammianus Marcellinus, who served in the</em> <em>army under him.</em> This emperor died on an invasion of Persia in which he failed to take the city of Ctesiphon after winning a battle just outside it. He rose to power after the sudden death of his cousin Constantius II in 361. This emperor's<em> Against the Galileans</em> was a written criticism of Christianity. For 10 points, name this last vocally pagan Roman emperor.", "answer": "<b><u>Julian</u></b> the Apostate [or Flavius Claudius <b><u>Julian</u></b>us]  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>This man's company was rivaled by former employee G.H. Thiel's organization</em>. This man employed the duplicitous James McParland as an operative. He founded a group whose insignia was an eye with the caption \"We never sleep.\" This former head of the Union Intelligence Service founded an organization whose undercover agents frequently protected \"scabs\" during strikes. For 10 points, name this Scottish-American founder of a namesake detective agency.", "answer": "Allan <b><u>Pinkerton</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Until 1958, this country owned the port of Gwadar.</em> A ruler of this country moved his capital to Zanzibar's Stone Town in 1840. This country's Arabian Oryx Sanctuary was the first ever place removed from UNESCO's list of World Heritage Sites. This country faced the Dhofar Rebellion. The Musandam exclaves are separated from this country by the United Arab Emirates. For 10 points, name this sultanate that dropped \"Muscat\" from its official name in 1970.", "answer": "Sultanate of <b><u>Oman</u></b> [or Saltanat <b><u>'Uman</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>A man who traveled to this island sought to become a scientist after playing with magnets at</em> <em>age six.</em> In the creation stories of the Nation of Islam, Yakub developed the brown race from the black race on this island. A book allegedly written on this island begins by addressing seven churches of Asia and later describes a seven-headed, ten-horned beast among many apocalyptic visions. For 10 points, name this Greek island where John wrote the Book of Revelation.", "answer": "<b><u>Patmos</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>The New Life Children's Refuge attempted to smuggle thirty-three children out of this country.</em> This country's occupation was opposed by Stenio Vincent. Woodrow Wilson sent troops to this country to quell the Cacos. This country disputes U.S. ownership of Navassa Island. Operation Uphold Democracy restored Jean-Bertrand Aristide to this country's presidency. For 10 points, name this country where a January 2010 earthquake devastated Port-au-Prince.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Haiti</u></b> [or R\u00e9publique d'<b><u>Ha\u00efti</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This man's ten illegitimate children all had the surname FitzClarence.</em> This man had an affair with the actress Dorothea Jordan. A Prime Minister under this man passed an act that resolved the problem of \"rotten boroughs.\" This man was the last British monarch who also ruled the Kingdom of Hanover. Earl Grey served under this king, who replaced George IV following his death. For 10 points, name this British \"Sailor King\" who was succeeded by Queen Victoria.", "answer": "<b><u>William IV</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>William</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This country\u2019s Bright Future party grew out of a party which promised to be openly corrupt.</em> Comedian Jon Gnarr founded the Best Party in this country.A 2012 referendum here approved a new Constitution that was crowd-sourced in the wake of the Kitchenware Revolution. This country instituted capital controls after the failure of the Glitnir bank in the 2008 financial crisis. For 10 points, name this Nordic nation with the world\u2019s oldest parliament, the Althing.", "answer": "<b><u>Iceland</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>One commander in this battle was court-martialed at Englishtown for failure to attack.</em> After this battle, British lit decoy fires to allow them safe passage to Sandy Hook, and Charles Lee was dismissed from the Continental Army. One person in this battle manned a cannon after her husband collapsed and brought water to her fellow soldiers. For 10 points, the legend of Molly Pitcher comes from what inconclusive 1778 Revolutionary War battle in central New Jersey?", "answer": "<b><u>Battle of Monmouth</u></b> Courthouse  {II}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>The instigator of this conflict had earlier recognized his rival Keokuk by the Corn Treaty.</em> During this war, fleeing members of the British Band were bombarded by the steamboat Warrior during the Bad Axe massacre. During this war, the Battle of Stillman's Run was won by a coalition of the Sauk and Fox tribes under its namesake. For 10 points, name this Indian war in which a young Abraham Lincoln fought.", "answer": "<b><u>Black Hawk</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This empire captured the Armenian King Arsak II after it was ceded to them by Emperor</em> <em>Jovian.</em> A ruler of this empire was crowned before his birth in an act where the crown was placed upon his pregnant mother's belly. Another ruler of this empire defeated and captured Valerian at the Battle of Edessa. This empire was ruled by two kings named Shapur the Great. For 10 points, name this Persian empire that succeeded the Parthians and fell to the Islamic conquests.", "answer": "<b><u>Sassanid</u></b> Empire [or the <b><u>Sassanian</u></b> Empire] (prompt on Persia / Persian)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The Revolution of the Restorers took place in this city.</em> The Mazorca security agency was formed following an uprising in this city. Several Montoneros were massacred at this city's Ezeiza Airport in 1973. A ruler from this city was supported by the descamisados. Residents of this city formed the Mothers of the Plaza del Mayo in response to kidnappings during the Dirty War. For 10 points, name this city ruled by Juan Peron as the capital of Argentina.", "answer": "<b><u>Buenos Aires</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Richard Rossi made a controversial film about this athlete that calls him a sport's \"last hero.\"</em> This man's namesake award was won in 1974 by former teammate Willie Stargell. In this man's last regular season plate appearance, he got his 3,000th hit and the next year became the first Latin American player in the Hall of Fame. For 10 points, name this Puerto Rican outfielder for the Pittsburgh Pirates who died in a 1972 plane crash while doing charity work.", "answer": "Roberto <b><u>Clemente</u></b> Walker", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Army officer William Buwalda was court-martialed for sympathizing with this person's</em> <em>oratory</em>. This person wrote an essay claiming that marriage is \"primarily an insurance pact\" paid for \"in dollars and cents.\" This editor of the journal <em>Mother Earth,</em> a \"free love\" advocate, had a long relationship with Alexander Berkman, who stabbed industrialist Henry Clay Frick. For 10 points, name this radical anarchist woman who was deported from the U.S. back to Russia in 1919.", "answer": "Emma <b><u>Goldman</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man fell out of favor after arrogantly constructing a temple to Artemis Aristoboule right</em> <em>next to his house.</em> After his eventual exile, this man served in the court of Artaxerxes I. Plutarch asserts that this man\u2019s love for Stesilaus of Ceos fueled his rivalry with Aristides. This man told of a prophecy of a \"wall of wood\" to gain support for his construction of hundreds of triremes. For 10 points, name this <em>strategos</em> who helped strengthen the Athenian navy during the Persian Wars.", "answer": "<b><u>Themistocles</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This work\u2019s third movement was originally titled \u201cWide Spaces Of Our Land.\u201d</em> A performance of this work was protected with an operation codenamed \u201cSquall.\u201d A theme in this work quoted <em>The Merry Widow</em> and is repeated twelve times over snare drum with a long crescendo. Best known for its first movement\u2019s \u201cinvasion theme,\u201d for 10 points, what Dmitri Shostakovich symphony was dedicated to a Russian city which the Nazis besieged for over two years?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Leningrad Symphony</u></b></em> [or Dmitri <b><u>Shostakovich</u></b>\u2019s <b><u>Symphony</u></b> No. <b><u>7</u></b> in C Major]  The <em>Leningrad Symphony</em>\u2019s \u201cinvasion theme\u201d was parodied in the \u201cintermezzo interotto\u201d of what 1943 Bela Bartok composition?  ANSWER: <em><b><u>Concerto for Orchestra</u></b></em>  {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>An essentially unchanged version of this text was adopted by the Savoy Conference.</em> An early change made to this text was the addition of an \u201cOrnaments Rule.\u201d Further changes to this text were later negotiated at the Hampton Court Conference. The first edition of this text was called by the 1559 Act of Uniformity and was primarily written by Thomas Cranmer. For 10 points, name this liturgical text of the Church of England.", "answer": "<b><u>Book of Common Prayer</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The founder of this group, Robert D. Stuart Jr., later became the head of the Quaker Oats</em> <em>Company.</em> A cartoon criticizing this group depicted its name on a roll of film along with \"The Nazi Transmission Belt\" and swastikas. Members included Senator Gerald Nye and businessman Robert Elkington Wood, although their most famous member was Charles Lindbergh. For 10 points, name this committee that attempted to keep the US out of World War II.", "answer": "<b><u>America First</u></b> Committee", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man was sent anti-slavery rhetoric and an almanac by Benjamin Banneker.</em> Solomon Asch studied prestige suggestion by attributing a quote to either Vladimir Lenin or this man. He signed a bill lambasted in a cartoon as \"Ograbme, the Snapping-Turtle.\" He coined the term \"wall of separation\" to describe First Amendment\u2019s separation of church and state. For 10 points, name this man who sent a letter to the Danbury Baptists and signed the Embargo Act in 1807 as President.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Jefferson</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This country's independence was announced by Ismail Qemali in the Vlore</em> <em>Proclamation. </em> One leader of this country used the secret police force Sigurimi. After coming to power, a king of this country swore an oath on both the Quran and the Bible. After the June Revolution, Fan Noli became regent of this country in 1924. This country's King Zog I was forced into exile following Italy's annexation of it. For 10 points, name this Balkan country once ruled by Enver Hoxha from Tirana.", "answer": "<b><u>Albania</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Peter Buell Porter was the only opposition to an election which this man handily won after</u></b></em> <em><b><u>the resignation of newly-minted Vice President Daniel D. Tompkins.</u></b></em><b><u> The Bucktails were a</u></b> <b><u>faction of Democratic-Republicans opposed to the policies of this man. Philadelphia lawyer</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u>Jared Ingersoll ran with this man in 1812. In 1825, this man rode along the </b><em><b>Seneca </b><b>Chief</b></em><b> to (*)</b> Buffalo and poured two casks of water into New York Harbor to celebrate the completion of a project sometimes called his namesake \u201cditch\u201d or \"folly.\" For 10 points, name this New York governor who sponsored the Erie Canal.", "answer": "<b><u>D</u></b>eWitt <b><u>Clinton</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>During this war, a commander threw some sacred chickens overboard after they didn't eat</u></b></em> <em><b><u>the offered grain.</u></b></em><b><u> This war was partly caused by Hiero II's conflict with a pillaging group of</u></b> <b><u>mercenaries, the Mamertines. A boarding tool called the</u> </b><em><b><u>corvus</u></b></em><b><u> was first used at this war's</u></b> <b><u>Battle of (+)</u>Mylae. Hanno the Great opposed this conflict, which included the massive naval Battle of (*)</b> Cape Ecnomus and featured a guerilla campaign in Sicily led by Hamilcar Barca. For 10 point, name this first war fought between Rome and Carthage.", "answer": "<b><u>First Punic</u></b> War [prompt on \"Punic Wars\"]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>After this man\u2019s trial and execution, his head was mounted on the corner of a granary.</u> </b></em><b><u>This</u></b> <b><u>man attempted to flee to San Antonio but was betrayed by a local in the mountains of</u></b> <b><u>Coahuila. Along with Ignacio Allende, this man led an army that was crushed at the Battle</u></b> <b><u>of (+)</u>Calderon Bridge by royalist Felix Calleja. He armed his congregation and gave a speech that ended \"Long live our Lady of</b> (*) Guadalupe!\" For 10 points, name this priest whose \"Grito de Dolores\" kicked off the Mexican War of Independence.", "answer": "Miguel Gregorio Antonio Ignacio <b><u>Hidalgo</u></b> Costilla y Gallaga Mandarte Villase\u00f1or  {II}", "metadata": "VP"}, {"question": "<em>T<b><u>he artist of this sculpture was criticized for his lack of pyramid structure in arranging its</u></b></em> <em><b><u>figures and the \"defeated postures\" those figures take.</u> </b></em><b><u>The artist's wish for this sculpture</u></b> <b><u>not to stand on a pedestal was fulfilled when it was moved in front of the Hotel (+)</u>de Ville. Stanford University has a copy of this sculpture group, which depicts men such as Pierre de Wiessant and Eustache de Saint-Pierre all (*)</b> dressed in rags, with nooses around their necks. For 10 points, name this sculpture by Auguste Rodin, which depicts six men of the title city about to surrender to the English.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Burghers of Calais</u></b></em>  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>An emperor with this name substituted mutilation for the death penalty in his reformed law</u></b></em> <em><b><u>code, the Ecloga, and ended the Twenty Years\u2019 Anarchy.</u></b></em><b><u> Michael the Amorian assassinated</u></b> <b><u>the fifth emperor of this name, known as the Armenian. The fourth Byzantine emperor of</u></b> <b><u>this name married Empress (+)</u> Irene and was known as the Khazar. The Isaurian dynasty was inaugurated by an emperor of this name who forcibly baptised Montanists and Jews and forbade worship of (*) </b>images, in part by smashing them. For 10 points, give this Byzantine imperial name shared with the Roman <em>popes</em> who crowned Charlemagne \"king of the Romans\" and censured Martin Luther.", "answer": "<b><u>Leo</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Documents important to this event included a unique mark consisting of a red circle inside</u></b></em> <em><b><u>two overlapping blue circles.</u> </b></em><b><u>A prominent figure in this event used a ten-dollar gold</u></b> <b><u>certificate that was no longer valid. Following this event, a man known as \"Jafsie\"</u></b> <b><u>delivered $50,000 to (+)</u>Saint Raymond's Cemetery. Norman Schwarzkopf, Sr. was the lead investigator following this event, which led to (*)</b> Bruno Hauptmann's death in an electric chair. For 10 points, identify this 1932 \"Crime of the Century\" in which the son of an aviator was abducted.", "answer": "the <b><u>kidnapping</u></b> of Charles <b><u>Lindbergh</u></b>, Jr. [or the <b><u>Lindbergh baby kidnapping</u></b>; accept obvious equivalents for \"kidnapping\"; prompt on <b><u>Crime of the Century</u></b> until it is read]  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A forest of this name is legendarily haunted by a horseman with antlers growing from his</u></b></em> <em><b><u>forehead, called Herne the Hunter.</u></b></em><b><u> In a play set in this place, an old man is trapped in a</u></b> <b><u>laundry basket and thrown in the river, a trick played by Mistress (+)</u>Ford and Mistress Page. That play set in this place was allegedly written after the history play (*)</b><em>Henry IV</em> to satisfy Queen Elizabeth's request to see \"Falstaff in love.\" For 10 points, name this home of two Shakespearean <em>Merry Wives,</em> whose namesake palace names the current ruling house of the United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b><u>Windsor</u></b> [or <b><u>Windsor</u></b> Forest; or <em>The Merry Wives of</em> <em><b><u>Windsor</u></b></em>]  {II}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The U.S. Armed Forces used this city's Moton Field for flight training.</u> </b></em><b><u>George Washington</u></b> <b><u>Carver died in this city on former Creek Indian land, where he had taught for decades. In</u></b> <b><u>an (+)</u> experiment run here by the U.S. Public Health Service, medical officials used the phrase \"badblood\" while lying to about 400 men who had been deliberately (*) </b>infected with syphilis. A university in this city helped select the first black \"airmen\" during World War II. For 10 points, name this Alabama city where Booker T. Washington helped start a vocational school for blacks.", "answer": "<b><u>Tuskegee</u></b>, Alabama [or <b><u>Tuskegee</u></b> Airmen; or <b><u>Tuskegee</u></b> University]  {II}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>I<b><u>n this country, the leaders of the Jewish Anti-Fascist Committee were killed on the Night of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>the Murdered Poets.</u></b></em><b><u> This country's \"diploma tax\" was opposed by the Jackson-Vanik</u></b> <b><u>Amendment and was used to stop (+)</u> refuseniks from leaving this country. Many Jews were arrested in this country following the revelation of the fictional Doctor's Plot. The term \"rootless cosmopolitans\" was used to refer to Jews in this country, which established a (*)</b> Jewish Autonomous Oblast in 1934. For 10 points, name this country where Zionism was opposed by leaders like Nikita Kruschev.", "answer": "<b><u>Soviet Union</u></b> [or <b><u>USSR</u></b>; prompt on \"Russia\"]  {II}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This song recalls \"a generation lost in space with no time left to start again.\"</u></b></em><b><u> This song's</u></b> <b><u>lines \"Fire is the Devil's only friend\" and \"Jack Flash sat on a candlestick\" may allude to</u></b> <b><u>Mick Jagger. This song closes as the Father (+)</u>, Son, and Holy Ghost \"caught the last train for the coast.\" This song's performer recalls crying when reading about (*)</b> Buddy Holly's widowed bride, and drives his Chevy to the levee only to find out that the levee was dry. For 10 points, name this song by Don McLean about the \"day the music died.\"", "answer": "\"<b><u>American Pie</u></b>\"  {II}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>In modern institutions, this text is often replaced by works written by Frank Netter or</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Keith Moore.</u></b></em><b><u> Richard James Dunglison published several American editions of this work.</u></b> <b><u>Drake, Vogl, and Mitchell created a student version of this work. Its last section is devoted</u></b> <b><u>to (+)</u>surface markings. Henry Vandyke Carter provided the illustrations for the 1858 first edition of this work, which was dedicated to Benjamin Collins Brodie and was mostly based on work done on subjects stolen from (*)</b> workhouses and hospital mortuaries. For 10 points, name this popular medical textbook written by an English surgeon.", "answer": "<b><u>Gray\u2019s Anatomy</u></b> [or <b><u>Anatomy: Descriptive and Surgical</u></b> or <b><u>Anatomy of the</u></b> <b><u>Human Body</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "EM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The second man to hold this position, Thomas Mckennan, resigned after eleven days.</u></b></em><b><u> One</u></b> <b><u>holder of this position fired Louis Glavis for whistleblowing about his deals with Charles</u></b> <b><u>Cunningham. After resigning this position, another man used the analogy of a (+)</u> milkshake to describe oil drainage. While serving in this position, Columbus Delano organized the Geological Expedition that led to the creation (*)</b> of Yellowstone National Park. For 10 points, Richard Ballinger and Albert Fall served in what Cabinet position that oversees the Bureau of Land Management and National Park Service?", "answer": "<b><u>Secretary</u></b> of the <b><u>Interior</u></b>  {II}  <b>Extra Tossup </b> This is a tossup provided for breaking ties or replacing a flubbed or erroneous question at any point in the packet. The power marks are provided so that it may be scored according to fourth quarter rules if it is replacing a fourth quarter question. The power marks should be ignored if this tossup is used to replace a first or second quarter question.", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>People in this country have put up barricades known as guarimbas.</u> </b></em><b><u>The murder of</u></b> <b><u>former Miss Universe contestant Monica Spear raised awareness of this country's high</u></b> <b><u>murder rate and sparked protests. Violence in this country is often carried out by militant</u></b> <b><u>groups called (+)</u> colectivos. This country's government was condemned for its arrest of opposition leader Leopoldo Lopez, and its failure to combat the high (*)</b> inflation rate has led to low ratings for President Nicolas Maduro. For 10 points, name this country once led by Hugo Chavez.", "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of <b><u>Venezuela</u></b>  {II}", "metadata": "JL"}], "bonuses": []}